We present GS-ProCams,
the first Gaussian splatting-based framework
for projector-camera systems (ProCams).
GS-ProCams significantly enhances the efficiency
of projection mapping which requires establishing
geometric and photometric mappings
between the projector and the camera.
Projector-camera systems (ProCams) are integrated systems
that combine a projector and a camera.
Geometric and photometric mappings between
the projector and the camera are foundational
to ProCams and serve as cornerstones
for numerous applications.
However, most existing methods are designed
for a specific camera viewpoint.
If these viewpoint specific methods are applied
at a novel camera viewpoint, it will be necessary
to acquire data and train the model again
to establish the new mapping relationships.
The state-of-the-art approach
for view-agnostic projection mapping employs
multi-layer perceptrons (MLPs) to represent scenes.
However, this method presents significant challenges
in terms of computational resources,
as evidenced by its slow training speed,
limited inference efficiency,
and high memory demands.
To address this issue, we propose GS-ProCams,
that employs 2D Gaussian for scene representations.
Since standard 2D Gaussian Splatting cannot capture
the interaction between the projector's illumination
and the surface,
we enhance 2D Gaussian Splatting
using BRDF parameterization.
We obtain the geometry and material of the target surface,
through differentiable splatting.
Then, we simulate real-world projector-camera systems,
using physically-based rendering.
GS-ProCams thus efficiently establishes
the geometric and photometric mappings
between the projector and the camera.
After training on a scene,
GS-ProCams can be directly applied
at novel camera viewpoints.
To train GS-ProCams for a scene,
we project various patterns onto the target surface
and capture images from multiple viewpoints using a camera.
This includes a fixed pattern for each viewpoint,
such as a digital speckle pattern to determine
the positions of the projector and camera viewpoints,
and a few nature images for model training.
After training on a scene,
GS-ProCams can simulate the target surface
with a novel projection
at a viewpoint that GS-ProCams
has not seen previously.
This enables various applications
of projector-camera systems.
For example, because GS-ProCams is fully differentiable,
it allows GS-ProCams
to treat projector compensation
as an inverse rendering problem.
By aligning the simulated result of GS-ProCams
with a desired image,
we can achieve projector compensation
for this viewpoint in the real world.
Due to its efficiency, our framework can be combined
with popular large generative models to achieve innovative
spatial augmented reality applications.
For instance, it can be integrated with
an inpainting model to eliminate objects
in the real world.
Similarly, we can combine with diffusion models
to change the appearance of reality
through text prompts.
Thanks for watching.
(See the principal manuscript for details)